Yuqi Tan

Address: 116 W University Pkwy, Apt1120, Baltimore, MD 21205

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/yuqi-tan-580983a6/ | Personal webpage: https://yuqiyuqitan.github.io/

Tel: 443-808-4156 | Email: ytan19@jhmi.edu

Summary

I am a data-driven computational biologist. I implement machine learning, statistical analysis, and cloud computing techniques on big data, such as next generation sequencing, to develop computational tools that I apply to stem cell engineering and tumor heterogeneity research. I am experienced in data visualization, including developing interactive web applications for data display. Additionally, I have strong communication, presentation, and leadership skills as demonstrated through teaching at various levels, giving talks at conferences, and leading graduate student groups.

Education

Aug 2015-now **Johns Hopkins University, School of Medicine**

BCMB PhD program, computational biology focus

Jan-May 2013 **Brown University**

Neuroscience and Biology, GPA: 4/4

Sept 2010-Jul 2014 S.H. Ho College, The Chinese University of Hong Kong

First Class Honor, Bachelor of Science, Cell and Molecular Biology

Publications

- **Tan** and Cahan. SingleCellNet: a computational tool to classify single cell RNA-Seq data across platforms and across species. *Cell Syst.* 2019 Jul 17. pii: S2405-4712(19)30199-1
- Radley, Schwab, **Tan**, Kim, Lo and Cahan. Assessing engineered cells using CellNet and RNA-Seq. *Nat Protoc*. 2017 12:1089-1102
- Kumar, **Tan** and Cahan. Understanding development and stem cells using single cell-based analyses of gene expression. *Development*. 2017 144: 17- 32
- Cui, Zhao, Xie, Wong, Wang, Gao, Ding, Tan, Ueda, Zhang and Jiang. MON1/CCZ1-mediated Rab7 activation regulates tapetal PCD and pollen development in Arabidopsis. *Plant Physiol*. 2017 Jan;173(1):206-218
- Mayer, Hu, Wang, Cardenas, **Tan**, Pan and Bednarek, SCD1 and SCD2 Form a Complex that Functions with the Exocyst and RabE1 in Exocytosis and Cytokinesis. *Plant Cell* 00409.2017
- James, Gu, Ramirez-Vizcarrondo, Hasan, Truszkowski, **Tan**, Oupravanh, Khakhalin and Aizenman. Valproate-induced neurodevelopmental deficits in *Xenopus laevis* tadpoles. *J Neurosci*. 2015 Feb 18;35(7):3218-29

Professional Skills:

Theoretical knowledge/courses: Methods in Biostatistics; Statistical Machine Learning; Data Structure; Computational Genomics; Next Generation Sequencing analysis; Single Cell RNA Sequencing analysis; Cell Biology; Genetics; Transcriptomics; Epigenetics; Personalized medicine; Cancer genomics

Programming skills: R, Java, Cloud Computing (AWS), python (numpy, scikit-learn, TensorFlow), HTML

Spoken languages: English, Mandarin and Cantonese

Research Experiences

Jun-Aug 2014 Vienna Biocenter BioCenter Summer research with Dr. David Keays, Austria Conducted project to identify somatic mutations responsible for microcephaly from trio-

exome sequencing and sequentially investigate expression of MAST1/2 during mouse

embryonic brain development

Research assistant of Prof. Jiang Liwen, CUHK, Hong Kong Sept 2013-Jun

2014 Designed research project to characterize Rab7's roles in the protein trafficking (fusion of

autophagosome to lysosome) via confocal imaging and sequential image analysis

Honorary fellow with Prof. Sebastian Bednarek, University of Wisconsin-Madison, May-Aug 2013

USA

Led project to identify and characterize protein-protein interaction (SCD1 and RabE)

using genetic, biochemical and imaging approaches

Jan-May 2013 Research assistant of Prof. Carlos Aizenman, Brown University, USA

> Characterized and statistically analyzed tectum neurons morphological changes after Valproic acid treatment with Confocal Microscopy and sequential image analysis

Leadership Experiences

2018 - 2019 **Biomedical Engineering Extramural Development in Graduate Education**

Internship Liaison

Match interdisciplinary PhD students with desire internships

Building events for career developments

2017 - 2019 **BCMB Colloquium Team**

Team Leader

Organize symposiums for PhD students (over 400 participants annually) to communicate their research

Design survey and analyze data to give presenters quantitative feedback

Presentation Experiences

Conferences:

- Tan. Oral presentation at Biochemistry Cellular Molecular Biology annual retreat (2019, Cambridge MD)
- Tan and Cahan. Oral presentation at International Society for Stem Cell Research Annual Meeting (2019, Los Angles)
- Tan. Invited talk at Cell Molecular Biology Symposium at Chinese University of Hong Kong (2018, Hong Kong)
- Tan and Cahan. Poster presentation at International Society for Stem Cell Research Annual Meeting (2017, Boston)

Teaching:

Jul 2019 **Biomedical Engineering: Topics in Stem Biology**

Instructor

Teach stem cell biology, developmental biology and computational tools associated to 27 high school students

Jan-May2018 **Computational Stem Cell Biology**

Teaching assistant

Assist 20 undergraduate and graduate students in developing and teaching of fundamental stem cell biology, cell identity, pluripotency, cell decision making and trajectory inferences

Computational Biology and Bioinformatics 2017-2019

Teaching assistant

Introduce 90 graduate students to basic high throughput analysis tools

2018-2019 **Practical Genomics**

Teaching assistant

Assist in a large classroom setting to teach researchers how to apply genomics technique in research